<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moderate answer to certain immoderate quæries laid down in a printed paper, entituled, A brief relation, containing an abreviation of the arguments urged by the late Protector against the government of this nation by a King, &amp;c. To convince men of the danger and inconveniencie thereof. Published for the good and information of Parliament, Army and people. By Charles Noble Gent. an honorer of his present Highness and Parliament, and a great lover of his country.</title>
            <author>Noble, Charles, Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E968_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866735</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866735</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 144:E968[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moderate answer to certain immoderate quæries laid down in a printed paper, entituled, A brief relation, containing an abreviation of the arguments urged by the late Protector against the government of this nation by a King, &amp;c. To convince men of the danger and inconveniencie thereof. Published for the good and information of Parliament, Army and people. By Charles Noble Gent. an honorer of his present Highness and Parliament, and a great lover of his country.</title>
                  <author>Noble, Charles, Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Marsh at the Princes Armes in Chancery-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 24 1658. Feb. 24"; the 9 in the imprint date hs been crossed out and replaced with an "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brief relation, containing an abreviation of the arguments urged by the late Protector against the government of this nation by a King, &amp;c. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168539:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Moderate ANSWER To certain Immoderate QUAERIES Laid down in a printed Paper, entituled,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Brief Relation, containing an Abrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Arguments urged by the late Protector againſt the Government of this Nation by a King; &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To convince men of the danger and inconvenencie thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the good and information of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Army and people.</p>
            <p>By <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harles Noble</hi> Gent. an Honorer of his preſent Highneſs and Parliament, and a great Lover of his Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Marſh</hi> at the Princes Armes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168539:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168539:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is a wiſe mans counſel, (and the wiſeſt that ever wore mortality, and was no more then man) <hi>My ſon, meddle not with them that are given to change;</hi> the word in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal bears a larger ſignification, as meddle not with thoſe that are ſeditious, thoſe that affect alterations and novelties. So that had I not taken up, and put on a ſerious and a ſolemn purpoſe and determination, to anſwer (to the utmoſt of my abilities) all ſuch Papers as ſhall come to publick view, that may any wayes ſavor of theſe ſeditious Novelties; I had laid this by, as being fitter for a ſilent contempt and ſlighting, then for any other replying. Yet when I conſidered that this, though it were but as a piece of Cork floating upon the Waves, yet it might bear up and bring with it an unſeen Net that may catch and entangle ſome unſetled and unſtable ſilly ſouls; and though it may be but as the Foam upon the Waters, as the Froth of the Sea, yet it may beget a <hi>Venus,</hi> an Idol that the inconſiderate vulgar may adore: Therefore I deem'd it not amiſs to lay to all my ſtrength and force to cut off all theſe <hi>Hydra</hi>'s heads as faſt as any of them ſhall appear. And here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole, it may not unfitly be inferred, what <hi>Bildad</hi> ſaid of old to <hi>Job; Can the Ruſh grow up without Mire? or can the Flag grow without Water?</hi> Can theſe ruſhy and ſedgy expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are ſet down in this Paper grow any where, but from mariſh, myrie grounds and principles? Or can the Flags that here ſpring up, (whoſe original comes from an Hebrew radix that ſignifies a brother, becauſe Flags do uſually grow up as in a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood together) can they intend any other end or purpoſe then to make up a Party, or to contract and beget a brotherhood that may abet and uphold the ſame ſenſe and opinion that this Paper holds forth? 'Tis much beyond the probability of a bare conjecture, that ſome ſuch teſty and untoward deſignment, is the projection
<pb facs="tcp:168539:3"/>that is aimed at. <hi>But his remembrances</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>are as aſhes,</hi> they are not only ſome vile and contemptible remainders of ſome better matter, (as of wood or the like) as aſhes are, but they are alſo ſullyings and diſcolorings of the ſacred memory of the dead, and that of no meaner a Perſon then of his late Highneſs: Him whom alive, he durſt not look upon but with conſternation and abaſhment, and whoſe Vertues, no leſs then Magnanimities, were ſo ſingular, ſo ſignal and ſo exemplar; his Aſhes he pollutes with his, his bleſſed duſt he moſt inhumanely does rake in, and rake up, with ſet purpoſe to dim and blinde ſome weak and rolling eyes. but this Deportment, J hope, will meet with no better ſucceſs, then they can have who ſpit againſt the winde, whoſe filth will return in their own faces. But he ſets a print upon the heels of his feet, as the holy Language hath it, he takes meaſure of every word, and of every action, and marks his ſteps to finde where he trod awry: when his gate was wholly upright and full of integrity, he weighs not the urgencies and neceſsities of State, which muſt be full of eyes, and look every wayes; and like a fair and a ſtrait ſtaff, which if one thruſt half way in the water it may ſeem to contract a curvity, when in truth it is ſtill the ſame: So reaſons of State lie in the water (as it were) to common eyes, and there may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to ſuch eyes ſtrange and unthought of irregularities, like the windings and meanders of a Brook, that may ſeem to run contrary wayes, when the ſtreams tend directly and through the moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Channels, (though with ſome ſeeming circuitings) to the Ocean.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in this Preface to the Reader, in regard that I ſhall ſay but little to half that the printed Paper ſpeaks on, in which is laid down the abreviation of thoſe Arguments, (as he ſayes) uſed by his late Highneſs againſt the Government of theſe Nations by a ſingle Perſon; and ſhall conclude with one Quere before I come to the anſwer of his Queries, which is briefly this. May we not take theſe bold diſputes and queſtiongs, as puſhings at the feet of his preſent Higheſs, as the Scripture has it? May not we fear that by theſe proceedings we may be brought too ſoon to ſay, Where is the Houſe of the Princes? May we not fear that
<pb facs="tcp:168539:3"/>though at firſt there may be but a ſeeming leakage, and a little breach upon the banks of our hopes in our preſent moſt illuſtrious Governor, yet that if there be no ſudden ſtoppage made, that there may be a wider breaking in of many and turbulent Waters both upon him and us? and that there may be a crowding, and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous rolling in of more ſuch Waters, that may even deluge us all? But that God that onely ſtills the raging of the Sea, and calms the billows thereof when they caſt up mire and dirt, let him allay and calm the Tumult, and the murmuring of ſuch People alſo.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168539:4"/>
            <head>The Anſwer to the Brief Relation, containing the Abbreviation of the Arguments uſed by the late Protector, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FOr the Arguments, though they are not in the abſolute terms (as he ſays) yet in the genuine ſenſe as the late Protector laid them down, I ſhall not ſpend much time upon them: Firſt becauſe it is in the dark to me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were ever ſuch Arguments in very deed and in truth or no. And ſecondly, if there were, becauſe the riſe and ground of all his enſuing Quaere's being hinged upon thoſe Arguments, I giving ſolution to them, ſhall give therewith an Anſwer (if not a ſatisfaction) to any thing that may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſed from thence. Only thus much I cannot but ſay, that the time and the ſeaſon alters the face of things very much, and that which may be denied of ſpecial uſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment at one time, upon a further cribation and trial may not be found ſo uſeful and concerning at another: So that the conjunction of State-affairs, as alfo the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentals that have been made by thoſe in high places what kind of Government would beſt go down and reliſh with the nature and conſtitution of this Nation, it having been alſo exactly viewed and weighed, and diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by the Patriots of this Nation, what would moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſute, and be moſt adequate and moſt conſentaneous to the general genius of this Iſland, as to the beſt form to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a Government in, that might have in it moſt of duration and moſt of <hi>utile &amp; dulce</hi> too; 'Twas given up by a general vote and conſent, that this our preſent Government as it is now ſetled, was the beſt. If that has been the ultimate and laſt Reſult of the Grandees of our Nation, who laid out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the utmoſt in their ſtudyings and contrivements
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168539:4"/>for the peace and ſettlement of their Country, (wherein their own welfares and concerns were inrolled and bound up) why is there then the voice of grudging and repining heard? Or why is there darkening of counſel by words without knowledge? Or why ſhould the Author go about to lead our Counſellors away ſpoiled, and make our Judges fools?</p>
            <p>So then, let there be from henceforward a ſlumbering of all animoſities, and a dead ſleep caſt upon all exaſperating and enviouſly fermented language: Let us hear no more of theſe expreſſions, which like flints carry ſecret ſparks of fire in them, ſuch as are theſe; <hi>The myſtery of iniquity going to be ſetled by a Law,</hi> (I ſuppoſe meaning our preſent Government.) And further (he ſpeaks it to the Reader) <hi>'twill coſt thee hot ſervice and ſorrow of heart to redeem thy ſelf and Country.</hi> Were not the Jews of old wiſer in their generation, then ſome are now in ours? They in the whole time of their Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over never named the word <hi>lechem, i.</hi> bread, leſt they ſhould ftir up a deſire in their children to leavened bread, which during the Paſſover was abſolutely forbidden: Why is there not that prudence, and circumſpection, and warineſs in our times uſed now alſo? that having had enough of War and garments rolled in blood, that now at laſt there ſhould not ſo much as a word or a whiſper be uſed or taken up, that may have the leaſt ſhadow of any tendencie that way? But there are ſome reſtleſs and diſſatisfied ſpirits that will not long be contented with any thing, but like waiward children that cry for a thing they ſee, which when they have in their hands they throw it away, and cry on ſtill. Of ſuch a querulous temper are thoſe that are opinionated, as the Author of this Paper is, who cannot at all palliate his diſlikings with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and beſeeming words; but falls on with — <hi>Fawning Courtiers,</hi> and <hi>Deceived Engliſhmen,</hi> and <hi>Calumnious aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens of Court-Paraſites,</hi> and ſuch like unſeaſoned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted ſpeeches, that can adminiſter no ſatisfaction to the Reader.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168539:5"/>
            <p>So that now I ſhall directly come to his eight Queries one by one, as they are laid down, and ſhall begin with that other Quere which he firſt layes down, before the eight, which he makes to be a Quere upon the whole, and ſo ſhall conclude with his concluſion, when I ſhall have viewed and anſwered to what is there ſet down.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole I Quere, <hi>Whether any man upon rational grounds can expect that the preſent Protector or ſingle Perſon (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Government) ſhould be more honeſt, righteous and juſt then his deceaſed Father was?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſome plants will not grow but in the ſhade, and as ſome fruits ripen not but in froſts, and as 'tis ſaid of the black thorne, that it bloſſoms not but in a ſtorm; ſo here's a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of ſuch a ſpirit, that delights in the ſhades and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of others vertues; here is a freſh apparition of that old evil Spirit, that had its chief contentment to dwell among the Tombs; and from thence comes forth and endeavours to infeſt and aſperſe the reputation, righteouſneſs and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the living: And whilſt he ſays, <hi>Can any man expect that the preſent Protector ſhould be more honeſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Father was?</hi> doth he not thereby infer, that there was and is a defect of theſe vertues both in the one and the other? And when he ſayes, <hi>The ſingle perſon (pretending to Government)</hi> with a Parentheſis, does he not intend it an abſolute Parentheſis, and verily believes that the ſenſe (the ſenſe that he means) would be very good, (and to his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very much better) if that was quite left out. And whilſt he ſayes, <hi>pretending to Government,</hi> does he not thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there is onely a pretence to this Government? So that 'tis not at all umbragious, but very conſpicuous, that the eſtabliſhment of the Civil Government, both as it was, and as it is, both in the deceaſed Father, and the ſurviving Son, is grumbled at, and quarrelled with. But I ſhall conclude this, becauſe I ſhall meet with more of it hereafter, with two ſtories that will pretty well ſuit with the two Perſons the Author ſeems to take offence and trouble at; The firſt is of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168539:5"/>the Great <hi>Talbot</hi> that was the fright and terror to the French; who being dead, and laid under a ſtately monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the French King in proceſs of time was inſtigated to deface his Effigies, and to take up his duſt and bones, and throw them into a River; No, ſayes the King, we durſt not look on his face when he was alive, we will therefore let him alone when he is dead: This might caution the Author to let our great <hi>Hero</hi> alone now he is dead, on whoſe face he durſt not look when he was alive.</p>
            <p>The other Story is of the noble Athenian; There was in <hi>Athens</hi> an Election to be made of a Governor, this noble Athenian was put in nomination, 'twas agitated and put to the ſcrutiny; ſome objected againſt him (and ſaid) he will do little good to his Country, he will minde his pleaſures and delights too much to minde that, and ſuch like words: Yet in fine, the vote went for him, and he was elected to the chief Government; when he was ſetled there, Now, ſays ſome of his Courtiers, is the time that you may be revenged of thoſe that oppoſed and ſtood againſt your Election, and ſaid, that you would never do good to your Country: No, ſayes the noble <hi>Athenian,</hi> I ſhall take no other revenge upon them but this, <hi>I will live and govern ſo, that I will prove them all Lyars.</hi> Such croſs and untoward arguings have been made againſt his preſent Highneſs, and ſuch, if no worſe doth this querying Paper hold forth, and ſuch as believe what this Paper ſpeaks will not be backward to ſay, that this our Noble <hi>Athenian</hi> will do little good for his Country: But you ſhall ſee what a gallant revenge he will take upon theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors, He will Rule and Govern ſo, with ſuch Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with ſuch Juſtice (and long may he ſo Rule and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern) as that he will prove them all Lyars. Now to the Queries.</p>
            <div n="1" type="query">
               <p n="1">I. I would Quere firſt, <hi>Whether the late Protector did not work over his Council to ſome things illegal?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is a departing from the old Rule, <hi>De mortuis nil niſi bonum,</hi> Of the dead we ſhould ſay nothing but good; and here
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168539:6"/>is not onely that that is not good, but that which is not true; never was his Council wrought over to any thing illegal: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, here's a low and a vile eſteem ſecretly laid upon thoſe Counſellors, which like leaden Rules in his opinion, might be ſo eaſily made to ſtand bent any ways; 'tis certainly a bold and a very ſegacious preſumption, to infer (as the Author doth by this Quere) that the late Protector did work over his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to ſome things illegal, which neither he nor they, nor any one elſe can diſcern, ſo as to diſcribe or give a name to them, ſo that when I have ſaid, that ſuch reproachfull things, may amuſe and ſtagger ſome weak judgements, and put them to gazings, and to doubtfull ſtandings in their thoughts, that this was the very end and purpoſe in the Author.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="query">
               <p>Quere 2. <hi>Whether Kings formerly, and the Protector lately did not wax wanton, and providing for ſome few of their Creatures, neglect the Commonalty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Kings formerly did, is not to come now into any diſpute; but by the Authors linking of them together, I ſuppoſe that I deem not much awry, that 'tis in his projection to bring a diſguſt, and an odium upon the one as well as the other; and ſince that of Kingſhip has been decryed, and has met with its doom and determination, is it not more then conjectural, that 'tis in the wiſhes and hopes of ſome, that the Protectorſhip ſhall meet with a ſpeedy, though not with the ſame exit; and how the late Protector did wax wanton, I think it is not in any mans power reaſonably to make out, and for providing for any of his creatures, (as he call them) never heard of any <hi>Sommerſet</hi> or <hi>Buckingham</hi> that he had: And for the neglecting the Commonalty, a thouſand gladded mouthes will ſpeak the contrary, Did he not alwayes deliver the poor that cried unto him? Did he not relieve and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the fatherleſs, the husbandleſs, and him that had none to help him? Did not the bleſſings of them that were ready to periſh come upon him? And did he not often cauſe the widows hearts to ſing for joy? And ſo I ſhall paſs from his Quere and the ſpightfulneſs that is couched in it, and come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168539:6"/>to the next, with the ſlanderous ſcandal that is in that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="query">
               <p>Quere 3. <hi>Whether our late experience of a ſingle Perſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not teſtifie, that though for a ſmall time he ſeemed to favor honeſt men and things, yet when he thought himſelf ſeated, whether I ſay, he did not then ſlight both them and it, and become a Favorer of the contrary? And whether our late Court did not ſhew more growth and increaſe of Rogues, Bauds and Whores, then in all the time of our Government by a Commonwealth:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here's a home-thruſt as with an envenomed poniard; here are poiſonous arrows ſhot, even bitter words; and the yet freſh, and precious, and bleſſed memory of his late Highneſs is ſtabbed and wounded with inſufferable obloquies. <hi>Scandala Magnatum</hi> was of old a heinous thing; it was ſo highly cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, that it always wore a moſt ſevere and ſignal mulct: And the toleration that it ſeems to make uſe of in this and ſome ſuch printed Papers, I believe is uſurpt and ſtolne, rather then any ways elſe indulg'd or licenſed. <hi>For a ſmall time</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the late Protector ſeemed to favor honeſt men and things.</hi> How ſmall a time? Indeed the whole time of his Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship (being well neer about that which <hi>Jacob</hi> ſerved <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Rachel</hi>) ſeemed but a few days. But does he mean that? No, ſays he, <hi>When he thought himſelf ſeated, he ſlighted both them and it, and became a favorer of the contrary.</hi> So that here's a double charge; here's a laying by and a diſreſpect, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing, a diſcouraging, a forſaking of his Friends, whom I ſuppoſe he intends by <hi>honeſt men;</hi> and here's an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion to, an embracing, and a falling in with (as he ſays) and a favoring of the contrary. So that this forked arrow wounds dangerouſly and doubly, and like a peſtilential contagion faſtens upon the very vitals and ſeat of life (as it were) of that ſo much renowned perſon, which is his honor; to render him wavering and unſtable, to render him a perſon given to vacillation and changings, and to charge him with neglects and ſlightings and diſregardings to his friends, or honeſt men or things; what greater vilipendings, what lower or meaner thoughts or words, or more diſhonorable, can be caſt upon any man?</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168539:7"/>
               <p>For the reſt of his ſo broad, and foul, and unhandſom, and unbecoming language, I ſhall paſs that by, as people do by ill and offenſive ſcents, with an averſion and flopping of the noſe: And ſhall ſay only thus much of his late Highneſs's Family, (which he ſo much vilifies and poſtpones to the Chimera's of a fancied Commonwealth) That it may be truly ſaid of his Oeconomy, what was ſaid of <hi>George</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt's</hi> houſhold, that there was in it <hi>Eccleſia, Academia &amp; Curia;</hi> And of his late Highneſs his perſon (of whom it may be ſaid, as the Jews did of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that his ſoul was ſuckt out of his mouth by God as it were with a kiſs) of his perſon I may ſay, as one being asked what a kind of man <hi>Baſil</hi> was, he preſented him with a Pillar of Fire with this Motto, <hi>Talis est Bafilius:</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Talis</hi> was his late Highneſs, all on a fire with a fervencie and an unquench'd zeal for the honor of God, and the good of his Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="query">
               <p>Quere 4. <hi>Whether a Confederacy has not been made abroad with our ſecret Enemies at home, that ſo a ſingle Perſon might the better ſuppreſs thoſe that ſee the wickedneſs of his deſigns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What wicked deſign this may be, and what that Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy is that he ſpeaks on, that has been made a broad with ſecret Enemies at home, I cannot gheſs no otherwiſe then by the Authors following words, in the concluſion and wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of his Queries, he ſpeaks more plainly there, what he ſays here but gutterally, and leaves to conjecture his meaning; I ſhall therefore paſs this over whilſt 'tis thus muffled, and ſpeak to it, as 'tis more bare fac'd, and as I ſhall there meet with it in his concluſion, and come to the next Quere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="query">
               <p>Quere 5. <hi>Whether the ſingle perſon now pretending to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though the Son of a ſubtil man, be a wiſe man, fit to diſpoſe of Commonwealth Treaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he that uſeth the word <hi>Racha</hi> (which ſignifies but piſh, or fie, or as other that derive it from <hi>Rec,</hi> which ſignifies empty) lies under ſo hard a reprehenſion that he's in danger of a Council, and if he that ſayes to his brother, <hi>Thou fool,</hi> be in danger of Hell fire; what a fearfull increpation does the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168539:7"/>Author of this Paper lie under, who is guilty of little leſs then the worſt of thoſe expreſſions, wherein is contained and couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a moſt bold, and a moſt notorious ſcandal; a ſcandal that contains in it all the degrees and dimenſions, and acceptations that a ſcandal is rendred, or maybe taken in: for if it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as it is laid down under the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is <hi>a ſtumbling ſtone,</hi> it is that; if it be conſidered, as 'tis called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is <hi>a gin</hi> or <hi>a ſnare,</hi>'tis that; or if it be conſidered as 'tis termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is <hi>a ſharp ſtake,</hi> it is that alſo; ſo that as it is a ſharp ſtake to offend and wound the reputation and renown, and prudence of his preſent Highneſs, ſo 'tis alſo a ſtumbling ſtone, and a gin, and a ſnare, to entangle and ſtrapple ſome feeble judgements, ſo as to bend them to ſome kinde of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that wayes tending, which ſhould it grow up into a belief, would prove a fearfull and a horrible, as well as a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtone of offence: 'Tis therefore well rendred by the Greeks, who when they would ſhew the abhorrency and the odiouſneſs that they conceived to be in <hi>Scandal,</hi> that they called <hi>calumny</hi> by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as, who ſhould ſay, it was a blaſphemy to calumniate, eſpecially thoſe in high place, whom the Scriptures have termed to be as Gods.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall haſten from theſe words, which are as full of ill vapors as thoſe Fens were, which <hi>Hanibal</hi> paſſing through loſt his eye, and are of as ſulphurous and ſtifling a nature, as report gives to be in the Lake <hi>Aſphaltites,</hi> which if a Bird flies over it, it choaks and kills ; and ſhall leave them wrapt up together as they be, and ſhall onely add this note in the general, that the ſteps of <hi>Machiavel</hi> are herein followed, who adviſed, That if any Prince were diſguſtfull, to aſperſe and calumniate him; for ſayes he, <hi>adhaerebit aliquid;</hi> no matter for the truth of what is ſaid, <hi>ſlander him,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will ſtick upon him.</hi> Theſe things in the late Kings dayes were look'd upon as of a moſt dangerous conſequence; and therefore ſaid an eminent Divine in thoſe times, <hi>If a Miniſter pray for the King, ſo as to ſend him the Spirit of Wiſdom; to pay for him that he may be temperate, mercifull, or juſt, was in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168539:8"/>effect to ſcandalize him, and to throw abroad a Speaking-Libel of him, and to infer as much, as if he had plainly ſaid, that he either wanted wiſdom, temperance, juſtice and mercy, or that he was a departing from them.</hi> Certainly, here's as much and more ſet down in this Paper then was ſaid then, and ſurely the remedies and experiences for the anticipating and prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſilencing of ſuch exorbitances, is as requiſite and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary now as ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="query">
               <p>Quere 6. <hi>Whether the good people of this Nation be not very ſenſible of the expenſiveneſs extraordinary of a ſingle Perſon more then of a Commonwealth? and whether they do not find a want of that vaſt Treaſure expended upon Baubles, Toyes, and trifling Gugaes, ſuch as we of late have had too much cauſe to ſpeak of? and whether the cauſe of the Peoples poverty has not been by means of purchaſing Land to the Family of the late Protector, as well as High-Spaniola Buſineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here's three things eſpecially found fault withal, <hi>That</hi> (as he ſayes) <hi>has waſted and expended ſo much Treaſure,</hi> and that's 1. <hi>Baubles.</hi> 2. <hi>The purchaſing of Lands;</hi> and 3. <hi>High-Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niola Buſineſs.</hi> By the Baubles, whom he further call <hi>Toyes and trifling Gugaes:</hi> I do ſuppoſe he may have in his eye the ſolemn and decent Funeral of his late Highneſs, and by the diſreliſhing and ſleight and ſuperficial terms that he gives it, 'tis eaſily ſeen how he was affected with it: But for the pomp of that Funeral, it was no more then the worthineſs of his late Serenity deſerved, and the Granduer of the Nation requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; And is it not Recorded of <hi>Aſa,</hi> that he was buried in his own Sepulchre which he had made for himſelf in the City of <hi>David,</hi> and that he was laid in a Bed (you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it a Bed of Honor) which was filled with ſweet odors, and divers kindes of ſpices, prepared by the Apothecaries Art, and they made a very great burning for him? And if the Scriptures allow of ſuch ſolemnities, as 'tis frequent in them that they do; why is it found fault with, and quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at now, eſpecially when they give ſo mean a Character of an obſcure Burial, as to call it the burial of an Aſs? For
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168539:8"/>purchaſing of Lands to the family of the late Protector, I think there was no ſuch purchaſe, (nay I am aſſured of it) that might any ways cauſe the peoples poverty: Treaſurers and other Officers to ſome late Kings (not to ſpeak of any Officers of nearer times)I am confident have purchaſed more to their families, then his late Highneſs ever did to his. And for the <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> buſineſs, it was a deſignment and an undertaking of ſuch noble gallantry, that had it been as well proſecuted and managed, as it was well adviſed, contrived and ſet forth, and had it met with that ſucceſs as was very probable and likely that it ſhould, never was there an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement from <hi>England</hi> ſet on foot, that could have brought more ſplendor and glory to this Nation, then that had done. But this miſmanagement or miſcarriage of one Expedition, blaſts and effaces the victorious and proſperous ſucceſſes of many other, which he that runs may read almoſt in every place within the bounders of three whole Kingdoms, with advantage.</p>
               <p>But (he ſays) <hi>This Nation is ſenſible of the expenſiveneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary of a Single perſon, more then of a Commonwealth.</hi> If he means by that Commonwealth the Long Parliament, (as I ſuppoſe he does) 'tis eaſily ſeen what a vaſt deal that was more coſtly: For what they gifted one to another, and what they other ways expended, as Records will yet ſhew, and the people of this Nation do yet feel ; 'tis eaſie to believe that they conſumed and waſted more treaſure (to ſpeak no further) then has maintained moſt of the Kings and their Courts ever ſince the Conqueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="query">
               <p>Quere 7. <hi>Whether the late Perſon ſet up, did not judge himſelf above Law? and whether he did not tyranniſe over mens perſons, reſtraining both them and their liberties? and whether the mercy be pretended to in the execution thereof, hath not been very cruelty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So now by this, as what has gone before, hand what follows, may not we think it high time to wiſh or look out for <hi>Davids</hi> Harp, or ſome other Inſtrument that may be as efficacious,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168539:9"/>though not ſo pleaſant, that may appeaſe and lay that evil and raging ſpirit that has entred into ſome ſuch opinionated perſons as this Author ſeems to be, who we may juſtly fear may not ſtick (too ſoon) to take up the Javelin, when there's nothing but handfulls of dirt already thrown upon the ſace of the moſt precious memory of his late Highneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The late Perſon</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſet up, did not he judge himſelf above Law?</hi> From what premiſſes does he bring in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference? when in the whole ſeries of his Government there appears not ſo much as a perſonal fault, that was any ways damageable to the Publique: Yet young and Infant-States and Governments muſt have ſtrong ſwadling-bands, which though they may ſeem ſtubborn, yet are of neceſſary uſe and concernment. For his <hi>Tyranniſing over mens perſons, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining their liberties,</hi> where was there any ſuch action that might juſtly have annexed to it ſuch an epethite? And for the <hi>mercy he has pretended, to be very cruelty,</hi> this is to ſpoil him of his chief and moſt embelliſhed ornament, and to raſe out one of his moſt Princely Motto's, which had very much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity with his Royal genius; and he ſate down beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, when he might ſhew his delight that he took in <hi>Peper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſe</hi> rather then <hi>Perdidiſſe.</hi> Much of his late time was taken up with a perpetual war either againſt his Enemies, or himſelf, and he was ſtill Victor over both. In all his government, that that might ſeem to bear any ſemblance of hardneſs or <hi>reſtraining</hi> (as he calls it) might be for ſome ſeaſon under the Major-Generals; and what was then acted, was not beyond parallels in former days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alfred</hi> (a little before the Conqueſt) who was ſtiled the Mirror of Princes, divided the Land into Shires, Hundreds, and Tythings, ſo as we finde it to this day; to this end chiefly to prevent any inſurrections that might otherwiſe happen, and ſo might juſtle, if not puſh down and overthrow a then young and infant Government; no Engliſhman then ſhould be deem'd to live legally, except he were of a certain Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or Tything, out of which he was not to remove with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168539:9"/>ſecurity; and if he did remove after ſuch ſecurity put in, then all the Hundred and Tything were fined to the King. And this Law <hi>William</hi> the Firſ, when he came to think of a ſecure ſettlement, found to be better to his turn, then any that he could deviſe; and he called it the Borough-Law, wherein the Commons of every Hundred ſtood Borough or Surety for each other, and the Maſter ſtood Borough for his Servant. And this Citadel, as 'tis termed, built for a Guard to the Publique peace, kept the Nation ſo regularly, that no popular inſurrection was ever heard of before the Conqueſt. So that the policie of theſe <hi>Major-Generals</hi> might be admitted to ſubſcribe <hi>bonum,</hi> however ſome of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagers of that Policie in their deportments may have miffed to have it atteſted for them that they did it <hi>bene.</hi> But whether this be meant or no by the Author, I ſhall not much be ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous of; but I am certain, the expreſſions here thrown out do deeply wound the Honor of his late Highneſs: And the Reputation of Great perſons is as the delicate skin that covers ſome delicate fruit; if the skin be ſcratched and pluckt off, the fruit will preſently diſcolor and fall away. So 'tis time that there ſhould be ſome care taken of theſe bold and rough fingers; and that his late Highneſs, who was one of the Glories, as well as the amazements of Princes, and one whom the chief Potentates of Chriſtendom at one time or other courted, that his memory ſhould not be ſuffered to be thus blanched arid trampled on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="query">
               <p>Quere 8. <hi>Whether the late Single perſon, to uphold his and his Courtiters voluptuouſneſs, has not been ready to uphold what Monopolies he found on foot, and likewiſe to deviſe new ways to the ſame purpoſe? And whether the Citizen has not had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Court-payment, and the Countryman (though ſad) of the ſpoiling of his fences, deſtroying his crop by them that belong to the Court, and that they pleaſe to call their game: And if theſe be the beginnings, what will the end be? And therefore for a cloſure I must ſay, What ſhall we ſay or do more, then the King-Protector has ſaid or done?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168539:10"/>
               <p>This is to uſher in his Concluſion a <hi>Muncer redivivus</hi> is very viſible in both; he in the confines of <hi>Turingia</hi> invented a Doctrine contrary to the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Lutheran</hi> both; he fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he had power to depoſe Princes, and ſubſtitute others, and that all goods ſhould be common, and ſuch like tendencies to popularity, he put to this an auſterity of life, and whilſt he ſeaſoned many falſhoods with ſome ſeeming truths, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate vulgar, that could not well diſtinguiſh betwixt them, admired, and ſwallowed all; the ſad effects that theſe things wrought, the <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> that wrought the cure, and what is ſo frequently recorded of them, can ſtill teſtifie: And how near the Author ſtears a courſe by this compaſs, any diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye may eaſily judge, and whilſt he proceeds in his ſo peremptory increpations and directions, he may ſeem to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us to renounce day-light, to contemplate onely, and to ſtudy by his candle. But why is there a redarguing of <hi>volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſs either in his late Highneſs or his Courtiers?</hi> certainly, there was more care taken to prevent the leaſt declenſion that wayes, then any Court in Chriſtendom beſides can ſhow.</p>
               <p>The truth of this is obvious to any underſtanding, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when it ſhall be remembred, that no man has paſſed without ſome remarkable puniſhment, that has but ſwerved from that Golden Rule of Temperance, that both his late Highneſs and his Houſhold ſo punctually obſerved; ſo that a Detractor is ſometimes a perſecution and a ſcourge to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for when he ſhall lay down too palpable and too perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſhall falſities, it will infringe and cripple his credit ſo, that he ſhall not gain a belief, though he lays down ſomtimes truths. I ſhall paſs therefore from his <hi>upholding Monopolies that he found on foot, and his ſetting up of others,</hi> as from things that have no proof with them, nor have they (with theſe that follow) any ſavor or reliſh, ſave of calumniation: For when had the Citizens ever better payment made, then they have and had from Court? Or where is any Country-man made ſad, by his fences ſpoiling, or deſtroying his crop by any Courtiers that follow (as he calls it) their Game? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168539:10"/>a horſe may be rid to death, (as the ſaying is) before ſuch querulous Language ſhall be heard, though the Author ſhould take the pains, and go in perſon instead of his Paper to all the Shires throughout the Nation; and whereas he may think that he has hit the Nail on the head, when he has added, <hi>What ſhall we ſay or do more then the King-Protector has ſaid and done?</hi> If he would but ſay and do with that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and temperature as the late Protector, but no King, has ſaid and done, there needed not then neither Queries nor Anſwers. And ſo I ſhall directly paſs to the view of his Concluſion, which when I have done, I ſhall briefly winde up all, and conclude alſo.</p>
               <p>And here he begins to unmask, and the Viſard that was put upon the fourth Quere, by the words, <hi>Confederacy made abroad with our ſecret Enemies at home,</hi> is here pluckt off; and here he comes to retaile what he bound up there in groſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and comes to particularizing, ſo that we are not left to uncertain and floating conjectures, he puts it to a ſerious weighing, <hi>Whether by preſent Action, and paſt Management of State Affairs, of ſome being Lawyers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(raiſed from a low eſtate to ſit in Council) and become great Favorites at Court, it may not be found and clearly ſeen, that they have a deſign to bring in</hi> Charles Stuart; <hi>For if they bring in a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and grant that, the next diſpute will be, whether the one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or the other has moſt right; and who have moſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> Charles <hi>or</hi> Richard, <hi>I think asketh no long time to Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here's no ventriloquy, or ſpeaking inwardly, or through the teeth, with broken and half expreſſions, but here's a down right quarrel to the preſent and paſt management of State Affairs; the miſ-actors herein he names to be ſome Lawyers, raiſed from a low eſtate to ſit in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) and to become great Favorites at Court; who theſe are (though it may poſſibly fall within the bounds of a probable ſurmiſe) yet I ſhall forbear their names, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they cannot be reaſonably deem'd to be ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168539:11"/>and ſo inconſiderate, (not to ſay improvident and irrational) as to be ſo ſolicitous, and to take up ſuch indefatigable induſtries, as to aſſert that wholy deniable in the Father, which they might be induced afterwards by any overtures to concede and eſtabliſh in the Son: Therefore his inference is very improper, and ſmall weight there is in his words, when he ſayes, <hi>'Tis clearly ſeen that they have a deſign to bring in Charles Stuart,</hi> and his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he renders is as far from the mark; <hi>for</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>if they bring in a ſingle Perſon, and grant that, the next di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute will be, whether the one Family or the other has moſt right; and whether</hi> Charles <hi>or</hi> Richard <hi>moſt intereſt will ask no long time to anſwer.</hi> To unravel or untie this knot, 'twill not be amiſs to caſt an eye backwards ſome ſeveral Centuries of years, and there we ſhall finde, that the Line Maſculine of Normandy expired in the third Inheritor, as if to begin the fate laid on all the future ſucceſſes hitherto, wherein the third Heir in a right deſcent, ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enjoyed the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> but that either by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion, uſurpation, or extinction of the male blood, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an alteration; that ſo to know whoſe indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably the Right was has puſled Parliaments, and has un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheathed the Sword often to determine; nay, the laſt has confuted the formoſt, and what the great Council has ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one wayes, dint of ſword has eſtabliſhed another, and that alwayes has been held an Argument of ſuch force and efficacy, (and retains the ſame vertue ſtill) that it may take up no time at all, to aſſert whoſe title's beſt, either <hi>Richard</hi>'s or <hi>Charle</hi>'s, for a pluckt Roſe will quickly wither: There might be added what the <hi>Switch</hi> at <hi>Croydon</hi> might poſſibly have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, by which it might very eaſily appear with what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection the Engliſh did put on the Scotch Yoke, when they generally reputed King <hi>James</hi> at the beſt but a King-in-law, without any natural affection to this Nation (as one has well obſerved) and if we ſhould liſten to <hi>Parſons</hi> the Jeſuite, who puts the <hi>Infanta</hi> the firſt, to fourteen titles to the Crown
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168539:11"/>of <hi>England,</hi> with that of King <hi>Jame</hi>'s, there would be much to do, to finde out ſo ready an intereſt as is talked on to <hi>James</hi>'s grand-child. But I ſhall leave this Goardian knot as 'tis now cut in pieces as by another <hi>Alexanders</hi> ſword, in the hands of the preſent Poſſeſſor, and ſhall ſay upon the whole, that this Paper holds forth, which being for the moſt part falſe ſuggeſtions, and ſo are like falſe Gems, which though counterfeit, they may be ſo ſet, that they may ſeem to have one good light to be ſeen by; yet that light is but an erroneous and a falſe one, and like an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> will miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead the followers of it into-perplexing and fatal, as well as dangerous precipices; and whilſt the Author is thus back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and behinde hand to acknowledge and congratulate his preſent Highneſs, Is not that in effect to withſtand and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him? and whilſt he caſts ſuch ſtumbling blocks in his way, Is it not to hinder him from ſtanding clear, though he cannot from ſtanding high? and whilſt he blackens and clouds the ſplendor of his preſent Highneſs, who is in all opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions a precious and a good man, It is not to induce a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon ſome, that he may be deem'd to prove a bad Prince? Is not this (in what he can) the ſetting of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt him, (as the Prophet ſpeaks) on every ſide, that they may ſpread a net over him (which God divert) and that they may take him in their pit? Is not this to build for him the houſe of the <hi>Moath,</hi> or to make for him a Booth or a Tent that may be removed and pluckt up at pleaſure? Is not this as the Eaſt-winde, which when it touches the Vine, it cauſes it to wither in all the leaves of its Spring, as the Scripture ſpeaks? or is it not as a ſtorm to hurle him out of his place, as <hi>Job</hi> has it? But let the great God of Heaven, by whom alone Kings and Princes Reign, let him be his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Salvation; let him be his <hi>Jehovah Jireth,</hi> his <hi>Jehovah Niſi;</hi> let him be his Lord Protector, and the Lord his Banner and Shield; and let him bring him from <hi>Ribroth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bataavah</hi> to <hi>Hazaroth,</hi> horn theſe Graves of luſtings, to Palaces of Paradices of Reſt and Tranquility; That he may be like
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168539:12"/>a handfull of Corn in the Earth upon the top of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; the Fruit whereof ſhall ſhake like <hi>Lebanon,</hi> whilſt we his Subjects (both in City and Country) may flouriſh, and grow green as graſs upon the Earth; let his proſperous Raign be to us as the Dew is to the tender Herb, that we may grow up ſtill, and never have cauſe to fear either a Drought or a Sithe, and that under him we may be delivered from all deceits and impoſtures, as well as the violences of men; and that all ſuch Papers, to which this is an Anſwer, may become as a dream, that when we awake the image of it may be deſpiſed; and that his Highneſs (notwithſtanding ſuch foul Papers) may meet with a long and a happy Government, and may become a Prince of all our Affections, as well as all our Countries, and that he may paſs from theſe <hi>Beth-maacahs,</hi> or Houſes of bruiſings, to laſting <hi>Beth-hanans,</hi> or Houſes of Grace and mercy; and that he may remain for ever, as a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and as a Royal Diadem; and that he may never be called <hi>forſaken,</hi> nor his hand be termed <hi>deſolate;</hi> but that he may be called <hi>Heph-zibah,</hi> and his Land <hi>Beulah,</hi> for that the Lord delights in him; and his Land ſhall be married.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
